Guide to the William H. Genné Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William H. Genné Papers
1917-1989
RG 79
Yale University Divinity School Library
16
(37 boxes)
The papers document Genné's religious work among college and university students. Material relating to Genné's workshops and published articles describe contemporary attitudes about marriage, family life and sexuality during the 1950s-1970s, and detail his work and influence in these fields. William Henry Genné (1910- ) was educated at Bucknell and Yale Universities and was ordained a Baptist minister in 1934. Genné was active in student religious work in various colleges and universities in the U.S. during the period 1936-1951. From 1944 to 1947, he served as the Pacific Northwest Secretary, College and University Division, National Council of the YMCA. Genné went on from this early focus of his career to become an expert in the fields of marriage, sexuality and family ministries.
Genné, William H., 1910-1997
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1910 Jun 8 William Henry Genné born in Philadelphia, PA
1931 A.B., Bucknell University
1934 B.D., Yale Divinity School; ordained at First Baptist Church, Waterbury CT
1936 M.A., Yale University
1936-1940 Director of Student Religious Activities - Michigan State College
1937 Mar 28 Married to Elizabeth Steel. Children: Nancy, 1941; William, 1943; Margaret, 1950; Susan, 1953.
1940-1944 Chaplain and Instructor in Sociology - Alfred University, Alfred, NY
1944-1947 Pacific Northwest Regional Secretary - College and University Division, National Council of YMCA
1947-1951 Chaplain - Pacific University
1951-1957 Teacher/Counsellor - The Clara Elizabeth Fund for Maternal and Family Health, Flint, Michigan
1957-1976 Director - Sexuality, Marriage and Family Ministries, National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.
1976 Coordinator of Educational Services, Montclair Counseling Center Program Coordinator, Geneva Point Center
1997 January 28 Died
For additional biographical information, lists of organizational affiliations, conferences attended, and works published, see Series IV, Box 30.
Scope and Contents
Following his graduation from Yale in 1936, Genné was active in student religious work. His files from this period, including those on the World Conference of Christian Youth in Amsterdam (1939) and the World Student Christian Federation Camp of 1939, complement other holdings of the Yale Divinity School Library in the area of religious work among college and university students. Genné went on from this early focus of his career to become an expert in the fields of marriage, sexuality and family ministries. In conjunction with his wife, Elizabeth Steel Genné, Genné conducted many workshops and wrote numerous articles for popular journals which described and influenced contemporary attitudes about marriage, sexuality and the family. His files document the issues and trends which dominated these fields, particularly during the 1950s through 1970s. The lists of conferences and organizations and subjects represented in Series III, Collected Material, indicate the scope of Genné's work.
The Correspondence of Series I deals primarily with arrangements for publications, conferences, workshops, and employment. In many cases, letters are filed under the name of an organization rather than an individual. Correspondence with R. H. Edwin Espy deals with the 1979 reunion of the 1939 Amsterdam World Conference of Christian Youth.
The Writings in Series II are those of William and Betty Genné. Genné frequently contributed articles to denominational magazines, other popular religious journals such as Christian Home, and to The Link, a periodical for soldiers published by the General Commission on Chaplains and Armed Forces Personnel. He also had articles on marriage, family life, and sexuality published in secular journals such as True Story and Redbook. The sermons and addresses in Series II stem primarily from Genné's years as a college chaplain at Pacific University and Alfred University.
The Collected Material of Series III documents the conferences, organizations, and topics that were the focal points for Genné's career. The chronologically arranged conferences range from international gatherings to Sunday school workshops. The May 1977 workshop at Trinity United Methodist Church entitled "New Life for Me and My Family" is a typical example of the Gennés' workshops on family and marriage enrichment. Of particular interest in the material arranged by organization are the files documenting the National Council of Churches' Family Ministries department. Important publications of the National Council of Churches include a study guide on abortion, collected denominational statements on sexuality, and resource guides on sexuality and sex education. The collected material arranged by subject comes from a broad range of sources such as magazine articles, government pamphlets and denominational publications. Documented most extensively are the topics of marriage/family enrichment and sexuality/sex education.
The Biographical Documentation of Series IV is biographical in a broadly defined sense. Files from different periods in Genné's life include material ranging from student papers to correspondence with the Selective Service System, reports to his employers, resumes, and documentation of television appearances. Three folders of articles about Genné provide concise information about his life and work.
The Audio-visual Material in Series V includes largely unidentified photographs related to Genné's activities as well as tapes, films and visual teaching aids used in presentations on marriage enrichment and sexuality.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Collected Material
IV. Biographical Documentation
V. Audio-visual Material
College students -- Religious life; Families -- Religious life; Marriage; Sex; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Young Men's Christian Associations; Clergy; Sexologists; Genné, Elizabeth Steel; Genné, William H., 1910-1997; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America; YMCA of the USA
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the sender or recipient other than Genné. In most cases, letters are filed according to an organizational rather than a personal name. Full names are listed only for substantive files.
  - Ac - Ah (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Retired Persons, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Baptist Convention, 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Am - As (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Association Press, 1953-1957, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Australian Council of Christian Education, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ca- Ch (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clara Elizabeth Fund for Maternal Health, 1950-1963, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cl - Cu (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ei - En (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Espy, R. H. Edwin, 1957-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Es - Ev (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - F (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - G - H (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - I (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - J (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - K - L (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - M (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Nar - Nat (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ne - No (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - O (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pa - Po (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Pr - Pu (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - R (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sa - Si (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sn - Sw (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Te - Th (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Today Show, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Tr - Tu (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - U (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - V (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Wa - WK (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - World Council of Churches, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Wo - Wy (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Y (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Writings, Series II
  Material in this series is arranged by format and chronologically within most formats.
  - Books and pamphlets by Genné, 1956-1979, 1989, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Books and pamphlets by Genné et al., 1956-1981 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Articles by Genné, 1930-1981 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Articles by Genné, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Book Reviews by Genné, 1961-1980, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Reviews and Advertisements of Husbands and Pregnancy, 1956-1958, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Bibliography of Genné's articles, 1963-1974 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Sermons and Addresses, 1939-1944 (Box 6, Folder 46-51)
  - Sermons and Addresses, 1941-1971, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
  - Notes, 1934-1976, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 54-55)
  - Manuscripts: A - L (Box 7, Folder 56-62)
  - Manuscripts: M - Y, untitled (Box 8, Folder 63-70)
- Collected Material, Series III
  The material in this series is divided into three categories:
  1. Conferences - arranged chronologically
  2. Organizations - arranged alphabetically
  3. Subjects - arranged alphabetically
  - Conferences
    - Baptist Young People's Union of America, 1925 Jul (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - International Convention of Religious Education, 1930 Jun (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - World Sunday School Convention, 1932 Jul (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Christian Youth Conference, 1936 Jun (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - World Conference of Christian Youth, 1939 Jul-Aug (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - World's Student Christian Federation Camp, 1939 Aug (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - National Conference on Family Life, 1948 May (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Pastoral Conference on Family Life Education, 1956 Aug (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Family Life Workshop Camp, 1957 Aug (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Employed Women and the Church, 1958 Mar (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - YMCA and YWCA, 1958 Dec-1959 Jan (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - American Institute of Family Relations, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 82-83)
    - North American Conference on Church and Family, 1961 Apr-May (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - World Conference of Young Adults, 1961 Jul (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Psychiatry, Religion and Sexual Ideals, 1962 May (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - The Case for Chastity, 1962 Jun (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Symposium on U.S. Population and Parenthood, 1963 Oct (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Canadian Conference on the Family, 1964 Jun (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Riverside Church Series on Sex and Christian Responsibility, 1966 Jan (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Fifth National Conference on Family Life of the Methodist Church, 1966 Oct (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Ecumenical Assembly of Church Women, 1967 Jul (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Marriage and Pre-Marriage Workshop for Clergy, 1967 Oct (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Flint, Michigan YWCA and Community Schools, 1967 Nov (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Perspectives on Sexuality, Sex Education and Mental Health, 1968 Oct (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - "Discuss-In" on Sexuality, 1968 Nov (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - Religious Education Association, 1971 Feb (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Pascack Ecumenical School Workshop on Marriage Potential, 1971 Feb-Mar (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - SIECUS Conference on Sex, Love and Intimacy - Whose Life Styles?, 1971 Nov (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - First Congregational Church, Verona, New Jersey: Series on Sexuality and Values, 1972 Apr-May (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - American Baptist Christian Education Conference, 1972 Jul (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - American Baptist Family Life Lab, 1972 Jul (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - American Baptist Men and American Baptist Women, 1972 Jul (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Chatham United Methodist Church - Christian Families in Today's World, 1972 Sep (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - Montreat Personhood Conference, 1973 Jul (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - Cave Spring United Methodist Church - What Makes a Family Christian?, 1973 Jul (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - Presbyterian Meeting House, Alexandria, VA: Lenten Series, 1974 Mar (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - Conference on Human Issues in Management, 1974 Jul (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Greenwood, SC: To Love is to Grow, 1974 Sep (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - Bucknell University: Human Sexuality Colloquy, 1974 Oct (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - Rochester Family Life Institute, 1974 Sep (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Changing Family Styles: The Church's Response, 1975 Apr (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Union Village United Methodist Church, 1975 May-Jun (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - Montclair State College: Sexual Problems, 1975 Jun (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - Ministers' Wives Conference, 1975 Jun (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - Christian Family Movement, 1975 Jul (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - Western Washington State College: Workshop on Sexuality and Human Relationships, 1975 Jul (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - Texas Council of Churches General Assembly, 1975 Aug (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - National Presbyterian Mariners, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - Ridgewood United Methodist Church: Making the Most of the Middle Years, 1976 Jan (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - New Jersey Medical School Seminar in Human Sexuality, 1976 Apr (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Hitchcock Presbyterian Marriage Enrichment, 1976 Apr-Jun (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Southern Methodist Univerity: Images for the Future, 1977 Feb (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Greece Baptist Church: Family Emphasis Weekend, 1977 Apr (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Connecticut Conference of U.C.C.: Spring Planting, 1977 Apr (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Trinity United Methodist Church: New Life for Me and My Family, 1977 May (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Maplewood: Parenting Workshop, 1977 May (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - YMCA of the Rockies: Family, 1977 Jul (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Wellspring Center: Clergy Marriage Consultation, 1977 Sep (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Adventure House: Sex Education, 1977 Sep-Oct (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - North Shore Unitarian Society: Marriage Encounter Weekend, 1977 Oct (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Warwick Conference Center: Marriage Enrich- ment Weekend, 1978 Feb (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - New Jersey Nursing Students Annual Convention, 1978 Feb (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Episcopal Church of Saint James, 1978 Mar (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - "Roots and Wings": Celebrating Stability and Change in Families, 1978 Apr (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - United Methodist Women: Human Sexuality, 1978 Apr (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Cleveland Heights Christian Church: Family Enrichment Seminar, 1978 May (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Human Sexuality Education, 1978 May (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Naramata Centre Growth Points, 1978 Jul (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Family Ministry, 1978 Feb-Sep (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Heidelberg College: Clergy for Heidelberg Day, 1978 Oct (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Grossingers: Ministers' and Mates' Retreat, 1979 Jan (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - New Brunswick Presbyterian Church: Helping Build Families Today, 1979 Mar (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - Fort Wayne Community Churches: Seminars, 1979 Apr (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Church Women United in New York State: Annual Meeting, 1979 Apr-May (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Rochester Community Church: Communications Seminar, 1979 May (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Montclair State College: Sex Education Conference, 1979 Jun (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - World Conference of Christian Youth, 1979 Oct (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Madison Methodist Church: Christian Families in Today's World, 1979 Oct (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Lawrence Road Presbyterian Church: To Love is to Grow, 1980 Feb (Box 13, Folder 150)
    - John Knox Presbyterian Church: Relativity Celebration, 1980 Feb (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Bound Brook Presbyterian Church: Building Christian Families, 1980 Nov (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - Community Church of Mountain Lakes: Christian Life Styles in a Contemporary World, 1980 Nov (Box 14, Folder 153)
    - World Assembly of Families, 1980 Nov (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - National Consultation on the Filipino Family, 1980 Dec (Box 14, Folder 155)
    - Building Ministries with Families, 1981 Mar (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - Sunday School Teachers Training Conference, 1981 Mar (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Pacific Council of Churches: Family Life Seminar, 1981 Mar-May (Box 14, Folder 158)
    - Family Education and Marriage Enrichment, 1981 Apr (Box 14, Folder 159)
    - The Filipino Family in Transition, 1981 May (Box 14, Folder 160)
    - Schools and Challenges of Family Education, 1981 May (Box 14, Folder 161-163)
    - Conference on Intimacy and Commitment, 1981 Jul (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - Presbytery of New Brunswick: Festival of Learning, 1982 Mar (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - United Church Board for Homeland Ministries: Family Life Conference, 1982 Oct (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - Rutgers University: Sexuality and Aging, 1983 Apr (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - Schenectady YWCA: Human Sexuality: A Family Affair, 1983 May (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - United Church of Christ: Family Life, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-1982, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 170-174)
  - Organizations
    - American College of Obstetricians - Bulletins, 1965, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 175)
    - Association of Couples for Marriage Enrichment Center for Parish Development, 1975-1976, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 176)
    - Association of Couples...- Newsletter, 1972-1975 (Box 16, Folder 177)
    - Christian Youth Building a New World, 1934, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 178)
    - Church Women United Family Life Advisory Committee, 1965-1984, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 179-181)
    - Montclair Counseling Center, 1977-1982, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 183)
    - National Academy for Families, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 184)
    - National Assembly of Student Christian Associations, 1937-1938 (Box 16, Folder 185)
    - National Council of Churches - Conferences, 1961-1983, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 186-191)
    - National Council of Churches - Family Life Newsletter, 1961-1980 (Box 16, Folder 192)
    - National Council of Churches - Membership Lists, 1963-1966 (Box 17, Folder 193)
    - National Council of Churches - Minutes, Reports, Communications, 1951-1984, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 194-210)
    - National Council of Churches - News Releases, 1971-1973 (Box 18, Folder 211)
    - National Council of Churches - Organization and Operating Procedures, 1960, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 212)
    - National Council of Churches - Publications, 1957-1982, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 213)
    - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S.- Conference, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 214)
    - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. - Minutes and Communications, 1973-1980, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 215-217)
    - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. - Newsletter, 1965-1971 (Box 18, Folder 218)
    - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. - Publications, 1969-1979 (Box 18, Folder 219)
    - United Church of Christ Family Life Priority Working Group, 1981-1982, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 220)
  - Subjects
    - Abortion and Birth Control, 1970s, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 221)
    - Aging, 1970s-1980s (Box 19, Folder 222)
    - Death and Bereavement, 1970s-80s, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 223)
    - Divorce, 1980s, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 224)
    - Family Finance, 1970s-80s, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 225)
    - Marriage/Family Enrichment, 1930s-1950s (Box 19, Folder 226-228)
    - Marriage/Family Enrichment, 1960s-1970s (Box 20, Folder 229-230)
    - Marriage/Family Enrichment, 1970s-80s, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 231-233)
    - Marriage/Family Enrichment, 1960s-80s, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 234)
    - Peace, 1940s-80s, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - Religion in the Home, 1940s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 236-237)
    - Religion in the Home, 1950s-80s, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 238-242)
    - Sexuality and Sex Education, 1950s-1960s (Box 23, Folder 243-244)
    - Sexuality and Sex Education, 1970s (Box 24, Folder 245)
    - Sexuality and Sex Education, 1980s, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 246-247)
    - Studies on the Family, 1960s-80s, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 248)
    - Substance Abuse, 1980s, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 249)
    - Women's Issues, 1950s (Box 25, Folder 250)
    - Women's Issues, 1960s-80s, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 251-254)
    - Youth Problems, 1970s-80s, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 255)
    - Miscellaneous, 1930s-1960s (Box 27, Folder 256-259)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 28, Folder 260-261)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 262)
- Biographical Documentation, Series IV
  The material in this series is arranged in a generally chronological sequence with folder headings listed to indicate the nature of each file.
  - Inspirational Material collected by Genné, 1917-1949, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 263)
  - Yale Divinity School, 1934, 1936, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 264-265)
  - Ordination Statements, 1934, 1936 (Box 30, Folder 266)
  - Marriages Performed by Genné, 1938-1949 (Box 30, Folder 267)
  - Notes for Worship Services, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 268)
  - Selective Service, 1940-1944, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 269)
  - Alfred University, 1941-1944, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 270)
  - Pacific University, 1947-1951, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 271-272)
  - Clara Elizabeth Fund for Maternal Health, 1950-1958, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 273-274)
  - Family Camping, 1954-1958, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 275)
  - National Council of Churches, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 276)
  - Southern California School of Theology, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 277)
  - Colgate Rochester Divinity School, 1959-1963 (Box 30, Folder 278)
  - Itineraries, 1959-1975, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 279)
  - Resumés, 1960, 1962 (Box 30, Folder 280-281)
  - Kennedy Assassination, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 282)
  - Television Appearances, 1963, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 283)
  - Drew University Theological School, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 284)
  - Adult School of Montclair, 1965-1966, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 285)
  - Profile, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 286)
  - Statement to the Senate, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 287)
  - Resumés, 1975, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 288-289)
  - National Council of Churches, 1975-1976 (Box 30, Folder 290)
  - Hite Questionnaire, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 291)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1980, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 292-293)
  - Articles about Genné, 1955-1980, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 294-296)
  - American College of Sexologists Certificate, 1979 (Box 32, Folder 297)
- Audio-Visual Material, Series V
  The material in this series is arranged by format and chronologically within each format.
  - Photographs, 1926-1982, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 298-301)
  - Tapes, 1957-1981, n.d. (Box OV1)
  - Phonograph Records, 1961-1969 (Box OV1)
  - Films, 1961, n.d. (Box OV2)
  - Filmstrips, 1967, n.d. (Box OV2)
  - Visual Teaching Aids, 1967-1975 (Box OV3)
  - Records and Books - "The Marriage Enrichment Program", 1970 (Box OV4)